Is your music missing that groove,
movement, and bounce that you hear in
professional tracks? I used to think the
solution would be something complex, but
two decades of releasing records and
teaching thousands of producers has
taught me that it's not some complex
plugin chain or advanced [music]
technique. Here's the secret, volume. If
you're only using it for basic leveling
and fades, that's like owning a Swiss
Army knife and only ever using the
screwdriver. So, today I'm going to show
you four common reasons why your tracks
feel flat and lack movement, and how to
solve it with the power of volume. So,
let's start with problem one, synths. I
bet you've added a synth to your track
only to feel like it's not quite sitting
right. That's because synths and pads
often feel flat and static straight out
of the source, especially when played
over rhythmic stuff like drums and bass.
Here I've got a pad and a string grouped
together. They sound okay, but they just
play statically over the drums.
>> [music]
>> So, let's get this synth grooving with
playing old volume. You can use
automation or whatever plugin you like,
anything that turns volume up and down.
I'm going to use volume shaper which
runs inside shaper box. I'm going to
load volume shaper on this group. Let's
start by loading this ramp up wave
preset. And without touching anything
else, this volume rise every bar feels
nice. It fits the groove.
>> [music]
>> Now I'll reduce mix to halfway so the
swelling is more subtle. This already
takes the track from flat to bouncing.
>> [music]
>> Now listen to what happens when I bend
this curve down. It feels lazy, more
laid-back.
>> [music]
>> Or when I make it steeper at the start,
the sound rushes in. It feels urgent.
>> [music]
>> Now I'll change the rate to half notes,
so the volume swells up every two beats.
And let's reduce mix even more.
>> [music]
>> It's super subtle, but that tiny bit of
movement changes the feel.
>> [music]
>> And we're not filtering, we're not
distorting, because I'm only shaping
volume, the actual tone of the sound is
identical. It's the most transparent way
to I believe to anything. Now, I know
what you're thinking, this feels like
sidechain pumping, but a bit slower. And
yeah, it does a bit, but something else
I do a lot is what I call
anti-sidechaining. Let me show you. I'll
load the ramp down preset, and then I'll
bend the curve up to create this inverse
sidechain curve.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So, if your usual pumping from low to
high is like breathing in, this feels
more like breathing out.
>> [music]
[music]
>> With the mix subtle, you barely hear it,
but you feel the movement. It stops that
flat sustain feeling that pads and
synths often have. And you can combine
normal ducking with an anti-sidechain
shape. So, here I'm using the sub note
at the start [music] of every bar to
trigger the compressor. And combined
with the anti-sidechain volume curve,
you get this [music] push-pull that
locks everything into the groove.
>> [music]
>> Okay, so we've looked at basic shapes,
but here's another example. In this
track, I've got a bunch of synths all
grouped. And on the group, I drew this
wavy volume curve.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The secret is to feel the groove that
the other sounds have already
established, and then draw a volume
curve to help your sound weave [music]
in and out and around that groove.
And you [music] probably noticed that in
these examples, I've been using volume
modulation on [music] groups of synths
together, which is a tip in itself. By
making all of your synths ebb and flow
to the same shape, it gives this feeling
of unity as everything [music]
grooves together. Okay, now to problem
two. You've got your synths and your
sounds moving, but what if they still
feel too polite? Sometimes what's making
your track feel flat isn't just a lack
of movement, it's a lack of attitude
giving that straight out of the box
feeling. This is where this much sharper
trick comes in. I call it hole punching.
Have a listen to this synth. It sounds
cool, but it feels too full on.
>> [music]
>> So, to make it tighter and groovier, we
can draw volume steps [music] to carve
out some notes in the rhythm.
>> [music]
>> I like how this now sounds choppier and
more syncopated.
>> [music]
>> Because music production is like
sculpture, you start with blocks of
sound and you carve away to make
everything fit. So, I'll often use
volume like a chisel to chip away gaps
in riffs and find little pockets that
add a stop-start feel. And by doing
this, I use this hole punching as a
sketch pad for new ideas. Now, I can
take what I learned from punching these
holes and copy the rhythm by muting some
of the mini notes in the clip. Although,
actually I prefer the hole punched
version in this case because at the end
of every bar, it chops off the
pre-volume reverb in a subtle but cool
way.
>> [music]
>> Now, you can take this even further with
advanced trans-gating. If you want to
see how to do that, go and watch my
vocal hooks video, which I'll link to
below. Now, there's another whole
punching trick that can make synths and
samples sound more pro. I grew up
listening to hip-hop in my teens. I've
always loved that certain snap and
swagger you get from old school sample
chopping. You also hear this in Daft
Punk's early records where the samples
are cut slightly off the grid. So,
inspired by that, I like to use volume
to punch these teeny gaps into a sound.
Here's with and without.
>> [music]
>> For more on this technique, I've made a
short video here on our Cable Guys
channel and a deep dive on my Minor
Chord channel. I'll link both below. All
right, now your sounds have groove and
attitude, but here's problem number
three. If the same volume pattern keeps
repeating over and over, your listener
stops noticing it and your track starts
feeling flat again for a completely
different reason. So, to overcome this,
think of how a magician uses slight of
hand. They do one thing in front of you,
but they also do something else out of
sight while you're distracted. Put the
two together and the audience is fooled.
And you can do slight of hand with
volume to make magic rhythms. Here's an
example. Here we've got a repeating
volume curve like we looked at earlier.
>> [music]
>> But then I'm automating the mix control
to keep the movement tight at first and
then blend out to something more
sustained to open up.
>> [music]
[music]
>> By doing this, the listener never quite
hears the same thing twice. And we can
go more extreme to make those
head-spinning rhythms you hear on modern
records. Again, I'll set up a simple
repeating shape, this time a downwards
ramp.
I'll set the rate to unsynced, so the
volume curve is free-running, not synced
to tempo. And by automating this from
fast to slow, we get this exponential
rhythm effect.
>> [music]
>> Quick side note, this also works well
with other effects like filters.
>> [music]
>> And you can also get wavy and automate
the smooth amount. Start with a
straight-edged wave and morph it to
smooth for this bubbly sequenced feel.
>> [music]
>> Many tremolo or volume plugins have some
kind of smoothing control like this. Try
automating it on pads and vocals.
Okay, on to problem number four. You've
added groove, you've got attitude,
you've automated movement, but your
track still feels off. Something's still
not sitting right. This catches a lot of
producers out. Nothing's missing
creatively, it's something small jumping
out and distracting the listener. This
could be a hit of percussion in a loop
or a spike in an arpeggio or a click
that catches your ear. Even a casual
listener who's never opened a door will
feel it. So, the solution is to get
surgical. Most producers reach for a
compressor to fix levels, but that's
like using a sledgehammer to crack a
walnut. I'm militant about using volume
instead because it's more controllable,
it's totally transparent, and it doesn't
touch the rest of the loop. So, if
something's sticking out of my drums,
I'll use volume to turn down or silence
any parts that mess up the groove.
[music]
>> [music]
>> And you can tweak the shape of the curve
to make it fit perfectly. Then use mix
to dial back the strength. And the same
idea works for cleaning up samples. If
you've got a click or a pop in a loop,
draw the volume right down on that spot,
and it's gone. No need to chop the audio
or load a de-clicker.
>> [music]
>> Or if a hit is feeling a bit spiky or
ticky, you can smooth its attack out
just with volume, nice and easy.
>> [music]
>> So, volume, it's the simplest tool
you've got, but that is why it's the
most powerful. Next time you need subtle
movement, chops with attitude, magic
interactions, or surgical fixes, you
know which effect to reach for. Because
remember, volume is your most powerful
chisel. Go to cableguys.com for more on
Volume Shaper and our
multi-award-winning ShaperBox plugin.
And to try the free, fully functional
demo with no time limit. And using
volume is one thing, but understanding
advanced distortion techniques will step
up your skills to the next level. So, to
do that, go and watch this video next.